welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
okay chickens feel calm grounded and
ready so welcome to the stoic
I am the Stewart of the stoic Peter
Lindbergh and the Stowe is a place for
us to go here and dialogue about what
matters most at the knife's edge of this
moment and today we have my buddy David
fuller everyone's favorite holy
journalist from rebel wisdom and David
and I had a conversation about kind of
conspiracy theories being a journalist
in this culture war or liminal war space
and this is an ongoing conversation that
him and I have been having for a while
now and we did this spontaneous jam
session last week
got some good feedback on the rebel
wisdom Channel and the idea today was to
have sort of a continuation at that
conversation not just with him and I but
the other people out the ZOA the tribe
about the stove oh that's for me so
what's going to happen today is me and
David are gonna have a little exchange
and if you have questions that come
alive for you write them in the chat box
and when we pivot to the Q&A portion I
will take you in and then you can kind
of reach your question to David and we
can have a kind of a conversation with
the clock of intelligence that emerges
so that being said David how you doing
today all right good yeah yeah I'm good
it's good so I was thinking because not
everyone might have watched the video
where we had that kind of conversation
and that but the general theme is kind
of the complexities about doing
journalism in this liminal state or this
liminal war and I wonder if you kind of
share your thoughts on that in the broad
broad way hmm I guess it's I mean
journalism
is a kind of loaded term I think I
prefer framing it is like how do we find
truth and that sort of problem of
finding truth feels very pressing at the
moment in the kind of overload of
information and I sketched out kind of
in our conversation and also in the
conversation when the films that I've
done recently about I looked
specifically at one story of London real
and David Icke and that that film being
banned by YouTube and all of the issues
around that that that brought up like
huge issues and I sense that like the
kind of the meta framing for me feels
like we're in this interregnum space I
think Zac Stein has called it the world
what's the world between worlds
education and a time between worlds I
think that was his book so there's sort
of time between worlds where you can
kind of imagine a Mike background I'm a
I worked for channel 4 news in the BBC
and I've made documentaries for for both
of them so I've been in kind of
newsrooms and part of the the kind of
traditional media machine for almost two
decades and then created rebel wisdom
initially with a couple of films with
Jordan Pederson and then a kind of
exploration into a lot of the same areas
that I know Peter you've covered on the
intellectual explorers podcast and so
just following the thread of what is
this emergent conversation and so kind
of being very aware of both the like the
the benefits of the alternative media
like covering stories that I wasn't
easily able to cover in the mainstream
and being sort of free to put out
everything that I wanted and not having
a whole load of editors that I had to
kind of keep happy and all of those kind
of really beneficial sides of being
outside the Machine but then at the same
time feeling that we are
and then using kind of Jordan halls
model of kind of the blue church the
sort of blue church enterprise which was
very broadcast very a lot of our way of
understanding the world in up until
quite recently was that we we put a lot
of the as sense-making capacity on to
that structure whether we realized it or
not on to academia on to the mainstream
media onto this very broadcast way of
making sense of the world and the and
now we're in this very sort of
decentralized much more decentralized
modality this much more digital modality
that has undermined a lot of that blue
church structure and for good reasons a
lot of that structure have become quite
Hollow quite corrupt and a lot of it was
a kind of like the Kathy Newman Jordan
Peterson interview I think is a really
good example of that it's like a
performative rather than actually trying
to get to truth it became like a
performative impression of truth seeking
and I think a lot of journalism had got
that way so I think like I'm not I'm
trying to hold this place of not trying
to defend the old structure because
people especially on YouTube a very anti
mainstream it leans very anti mainstream
so it's right but it's trying to hold
some of the values of that structure
which at its best had fact-checking
had some principles of trying to get
both sides of the story before
publishing something which had kind of
an evolved set of practices that I don't
see happening at all in there in the
alternative media and that really if
we're in this kind of interregnum
between the decline of that old true
seeking mechanism with all of its faults
we're not we don't have and you can kind
of imagine there might be a place on the
other side of that where we have some
kind of decentralized reliable
democratic way of finding truth we're
not there yet I don't really know what
that might look like it seems that we're
in this kind of very we're in the valley
between two potential kind of solutions
to the problem of truth and we can't
avoid
we none of us have the capacity to find
out absolutely everything for ourselves
no matter how much we like to kind of
think that we do we don't we always
proxy our sense making to someone or
something to some degree and realizing
that we're doing that how do we how do
we find the signal from the noise in
this heavily kind of weaponized and
information saturated and complex
environment and I kind of I don't know
how many people here perhaps how many
people here have seen the war on sense
making the film with daniel trachtenberg
oh great there's a quite a lot of people
I think he lays it out like lays out the
territory about as well as anyone I've
I've seen and so that's what I'm trying
that's the inquiry and I think as we
discussed in our film the other day
Peter I anyone he's coming at this with
an air of certainty that they think they
know what the answer is whether that's
kind of free speech absolutism or like
any ideological perspective is not
equipped I think we could drill down
into that like for me free speech
absolutism doesn't work it's not
sustainable in a world of finite
attention that has like I believe there
has to be some kind of curation which I
know gets a lot of people don't like to
hear on YouTube especially like I don't
think the the marketplace of the
marketplace of ideas right now is not
functioning well for many different
reasons there's a whole load of
branching off points we can go into on
there so yeah yes so something that's
alive right now is Steven Lucas's three
phases of power is coming to mind and
how he understands power is that there's
like decision-making power that's the
lowest level then there's non
decision-making power and there's
ideological power so another way to look
at it is like decision-making power is
just like the content the propositions
being exchanged like the obvious stuff
and then non decision-making power is
the agenda whoever gets to set the
agenda gets the influence the decisions
gets the influence of propositions and
then you can look at the the second
is the frame kind of the unconscious
frame that a conversation is agreeing to
and then the last ones ideology
obviously like who controls the ideology
and I think that Kathy Newman interview
with Peterson was like a brilliant
display of how those three things got
exposed because you know Kathy Newman
thought like oh this guy's gonna buy
into my agenda finding my frame that's
not gonna happen and you just sort of
like called it out in a way without
calling it out so and then I think I
just wanted to like I have a follow-up
question with that but with the blue
church in the machine what do you think
those things are that agenda that frame
of the ideology that's currently
influencing it and that's let's sort of
put a flag in the fact that even the
blue church frame is a is a useful
approximation it's not I think any of
these ways that we can talk about this
they're useful up to a point but they're
also obscure some stuff as well I think
like the blue church find a really
useful frame to use but I also and I
think I've also kind of become really
aware of the limitations of seeing it in
that way as well because I feel I feel
it can be too optimistic about oh well
the blue church is collapsing and we'll
just transition to something new I think
I think that's kind of naive and I think
if you really kind of think about what
that means it's a pretty terrifying
prospect
but I mean for me the frame like the
interesting thing for me that the focus
about rebel wisdom from the beginning
was the frame that I was most aware of
was the the limiting kind of
materialistic secular frame that I was
really familiar with from the from kind
of working in traditional media and
that's why I was so initially taken with
Jordan Peterson was because this was a
guy who was challenging the New Atheists
on their own turf and he wasn't easily
dismissed as being pseudo-scientific or
as being new agey or being any of any of
the ways that normally that frame is
defended and I knew how
like that kind of Richard Dawkins Sam
Harris frame was extremely powerful in
the media and as someone who's kind of
been interested in spirituality and been
interested in transformation and all of
these subjects and just really aware
that that's just not part of the
mainstream conversation I was kind of
very aware of where that's defended and
trying to do stories about stuff that I
could see where the cracks in that
worldview were were kind of being shown
up like psychedelic therapies for
example was something like I covered
from about 2008 onwards so I've I've
always been really interested in like
okay what what are those frames and how
is that truth how are those perspectives
defended and perspectives held so that's
something that I've been aware and
interested in from well before rebel
wisdom right and it's like what we said
in our last chat is that each minute
tribe has their own council culture and
you can also say they each had their own
Overton Window in a sense things that
you should talk about not talk about but
here here's at me at the edge of my
thinking I'm curious well you have to
say about this going to that go back to
the loops is three phases of power let's
just say you have the content the
propositions the agenda the frame and
then you got the ideology and it seems
like in our sense making space in order
to do good journalism we cannot be
unconscious of any of those layers we
have to have our eyes on each one of
them and being able to talk about them
and level-set with them would you agree
with that yes yeah I think I think that
yeah we have to be constantly aware of
what the framing is that we're bringing
to something because you can't operate
you can't operate completely without
being in some kind of a frame so you
think you have to be aware of when
you're slipping between them Jamie will
had a really beautiful analogy of like
the phone and the different apps on the
phone so you're using different apps for
different purposes but then to try and
be clear about what you're using at what
time at what time and then if you can
kind of be aware that you're doing that
right and I think like
what's really helpful into getting that
muscle that skill set of like being able
to spot the agenda and call it out is
what you and I have been playing with
all these different conversational
modalities where they're circling are we
spacing because you you go into this
sort of artificial container this
modality and the rules are explicit and
you have to be cognizant of not only
your own intention but either people's
intention and then you get the play in
that space and then I think if you you
play in a nothing spaces then you can
kind of see in the wild the
interpersonal while like oh shit what
game are we playing here and it's
usually the game that kind of like
instrumental eise's the relationship
towards something yeah yeah and there
are strong forces within culture and
society that are saying if you're not
playing that game then you're the sucker
but that's the whole that's the whole
vibe of business is this enforcement of
a kind of frame that if you're not
playing that game you're you're naive or
you're an idiot or Similan and so I'm
gonna turn to the Q&A in a moment but
they're going back that that framework
cuz I'm with find it quite useful right
now the top layer the ideology layer
which is something that I talked about
the culture war is like even though I
don't think every medic tribe has equal
truth claims or values I do think it's
helpful to act as if they are just to be
performed agnostic in order to speak to
each one of them and so what is your
like thoughts on when no one is certain
about what's the right ideology or
what's the right final philosophy how do
we negotiate like the mimetic mediation
thing how do you think rebel wisdom or
journalists how do you think we can
negotiate with all these different
ideologies at play
maybe negotiation is the wrong word like
how do you how do you hunt for the truth
in a way who ain't like you know there's
so many different ideologies that are
going to tribute it in their own way um
I don't know I don't know I think it's
probably a methodology thing as much as
it is anything else like there are some
questions like that there's a take an
example I mean there's some truth claims
going around at the moment that I don't
feel equipped to do an interview around
like some of these alternative medical
frames around but like I get that in the
comments a lot like what why don't you
interview Judi Mick of it why don't you
interview this person or that person's
like because honestly I don't feel
equipped to do that I don't I don't know
and I don't think that even spending
half a day researching her and
researching her claims I could then do a
good job I mean I might I might be able
to do a better job than most of the
interviews that I've seen so far with
that's my other my other concern if
we're talking about specific examples
that's I've had a bit of a kickback even
today of calling these some of these
people fringe medical figures and that's
Russell conjugation and that's me kind
of dismissing them my concern isn't and
I actually put that into the last film I
actually tried very hard to show look
there there was another doctor in so
there's these these people who are being
interviewed on London real for example
Judy make of its being one rushy Butare
Shiva ayyadurai
who without a value and I'm trying to
talk about it on the channel without
really evaluating their truth claims and
people just get so triggered by you
talking about them at all without going
into the content and I'm trying very
hard to say let's not go into the
content I don't feel equipped to do that
let's look at it as a phenomenon whether
no matter what you think about their
their claims they are getting a huge
amount of traction right now it is a
phenomenon that they are becoming hugely
popular and my concern with them as an
example
is that they seem to me to be only being
interviewed on very sympathetic by very
sympathetic people because they're
basically the mainstream is saying no
you're anti VAX
we're not going to talk to you but
there's all of these places that are
hungry for views that are interviewing
them in a very sympathetic way and so
their ideas are not being challenged and
there is no like and I tried very hard
in that to say look there's another guy
in New York who put out a video and said
hey something's going on what I'm seeing
doesn't look like pneumonia it looks
like altitude sickness and then a couple
of weeks afterwards what he was
observing is now part of the
understanding of what's going on with
Kovac so it's like I was trying to say
that you can't shut down you can't just
shut out someone who at the moment has
has by definition a fringe or a minority
view like these are these are important
voices and actually they're important
things that then get put into the into
the conversation but at the same time my
concern is that free speech without the
the idea is being challenged in the
marketplace of accountability is not
free speech it's something else
it's like profits propaganda and it's
not being challenged so that's part of
this kind of interregnum where we used
to have a structure that kind of worked
we'd have figures who would go onto
channels they would say what they said
they'd be challenged by journalists
probably health journalists who knew
that the area pretty well they then go
on to other other channels and people
would watch the previous interviews
they'd asked them questions based on
that you'd have this sifting of of
expertise and of good answers and you'd
have this process right now it feels
like we've got these self-enclosed
ecosystems and again I'm trying to talk
about this in a way that is not
dismissing an essentially use of a
conspiracy theory or alternative
viewpoint or anything people get like
Rudy your interview doing this
it's like I'm trying to look at it as a
phenomenon without judging or or
assessing the the value of the truth
claims like I'm trying to hold that
space of saying I'm seeing a phenomenon
that worries me because on one side
you've got the traditional media or the
mainstream that's not taking these
things seriously and thinking they can
do what they've always done which is
like get keep everyone they don't like
out the conversation and I don't think
that's gonna work anymore
I think that's an old modality I think I
even said in the piece they put out look
David Icke he's been saying the same
thing that he's been saying for 30 years
talking about this global fascist state
I don't think and I i I have some
respect for him for that he didn't like
for me someone that Alex Jones shifts
and just he finds what's what what goes
well it's conspiracy as entertainment he
moves he shit he's really believed a lot
of the stuff he's saying David Icke does
believe a lot the stuff you say and I
think Fred Plato in 30 years of talking
about lizard people and stuff that if he
if he'd only change that he could have
been way more popular if he'd gone down
the kind of anti-globalist route that
that Jones went down I think he'd have
been more popular but he was saying
stuff that makes it load of people think
man you're you're way too far out for me
you say some good stuff but you also
come in with the 12-foot lizards and the
the British royal family being cannibals
and all that sort of stuff and it's a
little bit too much fair Plato he stayed
true to his guns and I think so I think
on one side you've got the mainstream
thinking they can still get keep out all
of the alternative voices and that will
make a difference and it won't so I
think lots more people have to be part
of the conversation and that means
platforming in their language people who
they would have always said we shouldn't
platform in the past so that's on one
side and then you've got on the other
side this kind of uncanny valley of
these these people not being these truth
claims are not being subject to scrutiny
and so you've got these kind of little
ecosystems and I'm trying to talk about
this in a way of like look this is what
I'm saying
and I'm trying to hold this meta
perspective and it's really really
with conspiracy theory in particular
because people just lose their fucking
shit
they absolutely lose their fucking shit
in the comments especially and they're
like why aren't you talking about Bill
Gates
why aren't you investigating the plot to
cold most of humanity why onion is like
that's that's what I'm wrestling with
right now is the impossibility of trying
to hold a meta frame when people are so
religiously triggered by the subject and
are so obsessed with this is the most
important thing and that's what I'm
really wrestling with is just in maybe I
should ignore the comments but I'm also
I want to kind of be open to criticism
and open to self-reflection but at the
same time it's like this and conspiracy
theory is the thing that's kind of
overwhelmingly like this is the central
story as far as I can tell as a
journalist right now that is of interest
and needs to be needs to be addressed
but I feel so incredibly exposed and
yeah I feel it's such a difficult one to
talk about and because yeah just just
it's it's almost impossible because
people just immediately degenerate down
to you're controlled opposition and you
don't know what you're talking about you
haven't looked at this piece you haven't
looked at that piece so trying to talk
about it from a meta frame is is is
difficult and I'll also say yeah I'm
getting kind of a little bit activated
around it just just peak because people
say oh you're controlled opposition
you're scared of it it's like do you
really not think that putting stuff out
in this area is not like difficult
enough do you not think that yeah it's
like that that annoys me is like this
this constant like are you're just a
mainstream chill because you're not
calling out Bill Gates look fucking
loads of YouTube channels calling out
Bill Gates stop trying to make my
YouTube channel to every other fucking
conspiracy YouTube channel fuck off go
somewhere else
I'm putting the stuff out for free sorry
so if you ever want to trigger day
before just calm controlled opposition
I'm out yeah so I do have another
questions it's that's alive and then
we'll jump into Q&A so my read is that I
like we sit up at the blue church cuz
that can like quickly become like a
mongrel concept you know like a very
crew concept and my sense how you relate
to sort of like the the phenomenon of it
is that I think you would acknowledge
that the institutions that were
referring to as Abu Church have been
corrupted but the procedures in their
methodology should not be thrown out we
should kind of take the best of that and
repurpose it into this sort of
decentralized environment yeah and so
and I sent you this message on what
suppose it's like a ten minute message
and I don't think I got a proper
response for my so I'm gonna ask it
again and then I think it's relates to
what we're talking about here is it's
like the one line everything right
you're like a fucking talented
journalist you you know you've done all
this emotional work you have a great
platform it's a gold standard the
sense-making web in my opinion and a lot
of people's opinions as well but it's
almost like a one-man army you know it's
like it's David fuller and then you can
get squashed like a bug with all these
kind of like this conspiracy
thought-forces pair of political stuff
the you know the blue church stuff
what upgrading has a sense making
journalists army you know like let's
let's like let's release this this you
multiply you and all of us become like
sense making journalists in this space
so I just wanted like what you think
about that was a room thinks about that
and if how do we go about it I'd love to
know how to yeah I'm not very good at
that whatever the word is like when I
left channel for news they make they
make a video for you when you leave
channel for news it's sort of like a
tribute and and the thought the whole
theme of this 15 minute film was fuck it
I'll do it myself
with everyone in the newsroom going fuck
it I'll do it myself
so I mean rebel ISM is not just a one
man army Alexander Bynum I think's been
on here as well is is my co-founder but
in terms of the media side that's
basically me I shoot I edit I produce a
report I do everything myself
so that and and I guess the reason that
I do that like the reason I've gained
all of those skills over the last 20
years is because I I'm pretty impatient
I'm pretty single-minded and I'm pretty
yeah I'm pretty impatient actually I
think that's the main thing and probably
don't work well with us that's angry and
impatient therefore that's my air for
sure Peter I mean you've tapped on
something like that my area for growth
is how do i scale what rebel wisdom is
doing and I don't know the answer to
that I don't know I don't know what that
would look like to be honest but I do
think that's necessary I mean we've
talked about like ID I've also fairly
grandiose I do think there's a space in
the media landscape for a kind of vice
with heart like Vice is kind of
collapsing under the weight of internal
corruption too much kind of ideological
capture all these sort of things like
there is a space for treating these kind
of topics a sort of transformation or
spiritual like I can feel the outlines
of that space and I think that we've got
as good a chance of getting in there as
anyone but I don't know how to how to
how to go about it
yeah and just for people who are
listening I'm a Toronto correspondent
for rebel wisdom and so there's like a
personal interest to me like I don't
have your talent stack and the
journalistic sense but you know there's
an eagerness there to to engage in that
and then sort of maybe what
is probably the wrong word but to kind
of activate people who are inspired to
do it as well but the question is how to
do it so if anyone has any thoughts you
know we were curious to hear but let's
turn to some questions Tyson if you can
unmute yourself and asked David your
question sure thank you
let's see thank you David for being here
and like taking on more than your load
like I really appreciate you for the
work that you're doing and it's been
just very influential and important for
me lately and my question here is like
so with the whole dreaming of its thing
I myself I found myself like yearning
for like someone that doesn't agree with
her and isn't so sympathetic please like
interviewer where can I get this and I
can see the same for number of figures
and so you said something like you might
not you don't feel equipped or prepared
or something like that to do that
interview and so I just and and I even
found myself like I even tweeted Erik
Weinstein and I asked him like if you'd
interview her
because I have this sense like I just
want and it's not because I need to
because I agree with her or I disagree
with her it's because I want better
examples of like how this should be done
and I've and I've been following Bryan
Rose for years and used to really like
not yeah and I had a lot of respect for
him and his work so it's just I really
want stronger examples of how this
should be done and so I guess now my
question was whether or not we need new
platforms or if we need some sort of way
of organizing to influence these
platforms and then so what would maybe
help you feel comfortable doing some of
these interviews that are at the edge or
that that sort of risk all of that all
of that push back and so we have whether
that is like a platform where there's
like inherent agreements and
understanding amongst viewers of the
spirit of where that the enquiries are
coming from
yeah I'm just curious that comes up what
comes up for you they're like do we need
a whole new container and a whole new
environment and platforms or
is there something that would make you
feel more comfortable taking on some of
those conversations well I think just
thinking about that as an example say
Judy megabits I think I mean there are
some things that I would feel confident
asking her which would be some of the
discrepancies in the account or in the
sort of plan Zdenek film compared to
what's publicly available in terms of
her arrest and stuff like that I mean
that's fairly obvious what I'd be also
wary I think the way to do it I'm kind
of thinking as I'm as you were talking
would be to try and find someone who was
equipped to do that and to actually be
the person to hold that conversation so
actually have a three-way conversation
with someone who is who was medically
trained it would be able to go in
because I would be worried about I'm
what I'm we're wary of the optics of
being in that position of coz I just the
other thing is people don't get online
what what healthy come what healthy
challenge looks like and they basically
assume that you are like I had that with
Eric Weinstein when I when I did the
interview about Epstein and the disk and
I and I wanted to put myself in the
position of challenging him because I
was aware of what we were going into was
kind of controversial and also I don't
necessarily agree with everything that
he's saying about the kind of the
degeneration of the media I'm genuinely
puzzled by why they haven't like I don't
understand for example what panorama the
BBC documentary isn't doing something
about Epstein I would be astonished if
they weren't given the given I know lots
of the people who work on that program
and I know how it's a it's a big story
with big UK connections I mean news
night did the interview with Prince
Andrew and they were chasing that for
months asking Buckingham Palace like
time and time again to have an ingenue
so the idea that so I wanted to hold
that place of like pushing back a little
bit on Eric and then you see in the
comments people
look at this she'll mainstream
journalists like like people don't
understand what like that we've lost
this kind of ability to differentiate
between the person and the job and the
whole point of journalism when it's
practiced correctly is that it's a set
of it's a set of in the same way that
being a lawyer like being a lawyer
involves doing a professional job it
doesn't mean you have to believe the
person you're representing or believe
that the person that you're opposing
needs to be convicted it's like you've
got a job to do and you've got a job to
do within this and I don't think
especially online people just don't
understand so if I put myself in the
position of interviewing Judy Mike of
its and did did a proper job the optics
of that I think would would just lead to
me being and it doesn't really matter
what I've done previously like I think
in some ways I've built up a track
record in some interviews are taking
different perspectives but that doesn't
matter because most people will only see
me in that one interview will just go on
look at that fucking BBC journalist
she'll asshole attacking Judy Mick of
its and and that I think so I think
we've lost that ability I think we've
lost that ability especially on YouTube
we've got comments thread of
differentiating between the job and the
person and so those things are just
they're stuck together now and I don't
think we'll be able to kind of pull them
apart again so I think the only way to
do it would be to get on someone to hold
that other pole and then you've got to
think about who that might be and then
manage that conversation and probably
step into that role of trying to be a
kind of neutral observer and that's a
really that's a really tricky role to
fill
and I don't quite know and then you've
got the paradox now I'm wrestling with
this all the time it's like I do have
opinions and I do I feel more and more
tempted to actually bring my opinions
out and kind of to to play more of a
role but I also feel that what we're
really looking for is is is someone or
something to play a kind of trusted
mediation role and I don't know I don't
know how to resolve that because the
more I put my own opinions out there
especially about some of these
controversial topics the less I'll be
seen as someone who can actually kind of
hold a neutral space in in
yeah mediating it right that's
interesting because the terms that
Connor Barnes and I did in that culture
paper is a dirty bias or clean bias and
it's like if like clean biases is
admitting your bias and then trying to
be searched for the truth but if you
don't do that there's this like sense of
inauthenticity about this performative
neutrality and you have like a dirty
biased feeling associated with that so
it is very very challenging I think to
engage with I don't think anyone's
really got it right yet except maybe
you're the closest one well I don't know
I'm starting to
I think everyone's gonna lose their shit
with the next film on cut outs but don't
we well we just might see angry fuller
just be angry at the film that I
actually I just thought that I might do
that I mean that's one other I might
just put out something where I just ran
and just say look fucking sort it out
stop asking that in the comments and if
you're not up to it then find another
channel because I want more from you
guys in this this is just not good
enough
nice we got some yeses in the chats and
shaking heads so the story proves let's
just put it that way so we had version
madness Helen I'm not taking it anymore
very good perfect
I think I mean honestly I I'm seriously
thinking about that because otherwise
it's gonna come out kind of
subconsciously anyway it's like right
guys shape up stop reading the comments
kind of I I am trying not to take it as
seriously and Joe Rogan does say don't
look at the comments but at the same
time the whole project is framed around
being open to feedback and being like I
don't know how to do that I don't know
how because I the comments thread is
just not conducive to like genuine
dialogue of genuine feedback and when
you see a good comment where someone's
actually taken some time to put
something together well that's unusual
but then people get very upset if you
delete them I mean I do delete some
comments if it's just like not if it's
just completely reactive and not taking
any taking us forward then I I'll admit
I have deleted you YouTube comments but
yeah I don't
know where the right place to sort of
engage in those dialogues is because I
don't argue on Facebook much anymore
that's because I at the store we for I
disabled all YouTube comments even
though we post these because like you
guys think about you cuz I was featured
on the channel three times and then this
like you gravitate towards like they're
like the stupidest comments like who's
this pretentious guy went to the fuck
and then you just like you go into it
and I'm like man let's be exhausting to
be full or just like crooning this shit
all the time so I got my hat off to you
for engaging that struggle okay so Shawn
Williams if you can unmute yourself ask
your question to fuller
great thanks David I think this question
is hard to answer to ask and even harder
to answer you mentioned something about
free speech absolutist elute ISM sort of
being opposed to curation when I think
of creation I think of one person using
kind of their unified sense to sort of
decide like what is worth sharing do you
see something in between free speech
absolute and sort of being on the
opposite side of that where you're just
using like multiple people's senses and
allowing them to sort of do their own
thing is there some way to sort of
synthesize these things to have some
kind of what would you say like a
distributed creation type thing or is
that I think of Daniels Martin burgers
saying something like that systems are
pop impossible to retrofit if they're
built on the wrong axioms that's sort of
like a more that kind of fills me with
despair to think of it in that way or is
it more like well the transition is
possible because it's necessary like do
you see some kind of like synthesis
between these two things to provide some
kind of distributed creation hard to ask
and answer I don't know I don't know I
don't know what it would look like I'm
I've seen so many
I've seen the failure conditions of like
the main of the the alternative media
and a lot of it is is driven by my
audience capture how do you avoid
audience capture when you've got in
these feedback loops and how do you not
get caught in in that I don't know what
the answer to curation is I mean it's
certainly a much more important factor
than I think a lot of people realize
[Music]
yeah I don't know I mean I spoke to
Douglas Murray the other day and he he
actually said it in previous one it's
like we can't imagine especially in the
in the u.s. we can't imagine what that
would look like like who who would you
give that power to like if you're going
to say at some point someone has to make
that decision and I think I think most
of us recognize that there are there are
some examples whether that's child
pornography or whether that's far-right
recruiting or whether that's incitement
to violence that there have to be some
some restrictions like there can't be a
complete free-for-all so at some point
you unless you are a complete absolutist
which I mean I think most people on
YouTube especially a kind of naive
absolutist because I haven't really
thought it through they're just like you
can't delete my comment I can say
whatever I want and it comes from that
kind of instinctive place about do
whatever the fuck I want where where I
want which I I don't agree with that I
mean I I do like I I don't think I am
obliged to have any one post on my
facebook wall I don't think I'm obliged
to to put up with that if I don't want
someone to post on my facebook wall I
think I'm within my rights to say no I'm
not having that here so I think the same
thing is true of the rebel wisdom
YouTube channel I'd like to find a
solution to the problem of a quality
discussion in the comment
and I've got no fucking idea what that's
gonna look like because it doesn't seem
designed for that positive I mean it
could I could imagine it becoming a pot
a self-regulating system I think there
is something about what are the
conditions for creating a
self-regulating system that is solid and
that is organic and that becomes self
policing and I don't know and I don't I
think that's probably less I think a
healthy ecosystem will do most of the
work for us
but what does that look like and how do
you create it and and how do you create
a healthy community which is again
something that Douglas Murray said in
the interview yesterday which is
actually a lot of the question of free
speech and voices that are like
misinformation and all these sort of
things are there a question of societal
health more than they are of a question
of do you ban this person or do you
censor this person because in a healthy
society someone pushing a miracle cure
or someone or like David Icke is not
going to like it David Icke would not be
getting the traction he's got right now
if it wasn't for the fact that we're all
freaked out and the fact that he speaks
with such authority and and I'm not
saying that David Icke has no signal I
think the important thing like whenever
you talk about these is that David Icke
clearly has some signal I think he's
actually there's there's some sort of
metaphorical truth in a lot of ways
saying even if I don't think there's a
lot of factual truth but that's the
other problem this is a slight different
issue but it's like it's impossible to
talk about any of these things without
layering in kind of like context upon
context and condition upon condition and
then when I'm putting a video together
it just becomes unwieldy because I can't
put enough context to avoid all of the
potential objections and people saying
oh well you're not including there so
you're not including that so it's yeah
but going back to your main point I
think it's okay I think and as you can
tell maybe I'm kind of thinking about
this in real time as I'm answering you
and kind of maybe coming to more of a
think it's a case of I think it's a case
of the health of the ecosystem rather
than it is a set of principles and it's
like how do we create healthy ecosystems
that's the question I think fertile soil
yeah cool
Jordan you had a question hey David
am I on right okay so I am you saying
that you're you very terrified of this
idea of the post blue church when the
collapse finally comes and why don't you
comment on exactly why that is so scary
I think if you're not scared by that
prospect you haven't really understood
what it means like just take just take
so the blue church is pretty much
everything I mean if you if you look at
it quite narrowly as like and I think a
lot of people who are kind of clapping
on the end of the blue church looking at
it quite narrowly as sort of liberal
Hollywood and the New York Times and all
of those kind of institutions that I
think a lot of us think have become at
least partial or not not helpful but if
you realize that the blue church is the
entire activation capacity of the entire
world that was built up after the Second
World War
like it was all of these systems all of
these structures based on we had this
huge clash of different worldviews that
culminate in the second world war
fascism communism being at that time the
most vibrant systems they looked like
the most likely solution and then in the
aftermath of world war two you had all
of these people who'd gone through that
incredibly traumatic learning experience
building all these all these systems the
World Bank the UN the all of these
systems which all have their flaws as
well but they they kind of what the IMF
I mean they kind of worked and they
worked like it
we shouldn't take for granted that
situation we've had over the last 70 or
80 years and I think far too many of us
are like this is not we can look for all
the corruption and all of the holes and
all of the things that was leaving out
but for fuck's sake look around you kind
of as Peterson says like look around
what a fucking miracle it is that we
don't live in a society like I mean I've
I've worked around the world in Haiti in
Africa and like these we are we're in a
pretty miraculous situation and I just
look for example at like this blue
church this blue church entity in
foreign affairs which is the area I know
very well and I look at the way that
Trump and other forces are just
obliterating all of these structures and
we're going back to great power politics
we're going back to might makes right
we're going back to and might makes
right in a world where China is probably
going to come out of this crisis as the
dominant superpower with everything
they're doing and they are arguably on a
par with some of the stuff they're doing
is on a par with some some of the stuff
that the Germany was doing in the 1930s
and 40s like do you realize what that
means do you realize what the disruption
of that system that we've taken for
granted actually means in practice like
do you realize how much that like we
talked about kind of the caterpillar and
the butterfly like that liquification
process it's fucking is gonna be fucking
terrifying and like do you do you know
what that like everyone I think who I've
worked with like who kind of understands
the way the world works from a kind of
institutions perspective is just like oh
my fucking god we are and who knows what
it's going to be it's gonna be I mean
nothing's off the table I mean warfare
including nuclear war is on the table
massive societal uprooting like we've
got no idea what the society on the
other side of this is gonna look like
and there's so many different ways it
could go so that's what I mean by
I think this is one thing I'd like to
have a conversation with Jordan Hall
about even from a sense-making
perspective like if we lose the
institutions of the blue church we'd
lose the institutional memory of those
like newsrooms of making sense of the
world like without anything meaningful
to on the other side of that that's a
I'm I'm up for that as a kind of thought
experiment and I'm up for it as a like
okay let's take the plunge and I but
it's like we don't know what the world
on the other side of it's gonna look
like I have faith that something will
come to break our fall that we really
are jumping off a cliff
and I don't yeah I think it'd convert it
can very easily feel quite naive to say
oh well yeah the blue churches die and
then we've got this kind of insurgency
or this network solution on the other
side it's like I'm not seeing that
Network solution and things seem to be
falling apart very very quickly we're
not gonna be caught by anything in the
near term so that that's does that
answer your your question yeah thanks a
lot okay it's okay I do be the naive
waiting for the thing to crash a lot
innit I do I tend to like bias my
thinking away from what you're talking
about so thanks a lot I think I like I
am genuinely an optimist I think we'll
be okay but I think unless you really
face up to what what that means like
what I think we're just in so much
danger of magical thinking and I see so
much magical thinking in this space like
can you face that full up can you can
you look that full in the face can you
look what that is likely to mean full in
the face and still keep the positivity
and the optimism on the other side so
Jamie wheel did an amazing talk which is
on a maybe ask Peter to send it out
afterwards call it was a it was a
workshop we did called what was it sense
making in an age of existential risk
collective sense making an age of
existential risk where he just laid all
of that out beautifully and at the time
when he gave it this was last year I
thought wow Jamie's gone off the deep
end he's way way more apocalyptic than
I've ever heard him I don't know if I
agree with him now I kind of think oh
yeah he was he was ahead of the curve he
and that's the other thing as I've kind
of felt in this exploration like I've
held these two pieces like Jordan
Pederson and Steven Pinker of lower and
the best time to ever be alive things
are getting better and better and and
also speaking to a lot of people who
were talking about existential risk and
we're really kind of laying out a very
different picture it's like can I hold
both of these and I feel like I did in
the inquiry on the channel but as soon
as the pandemic hit and it was just like
okay systemic cascade looks pretty
obvious to me now
okay now I'm now I'm collapsing into I
think I think the ideas space of these
possibilities his collapse quite
radically in the last few months and I'm
one of our zoom calls the other day with
someone who was one of our one of our
members she's in a Jordan Peterson
discussion group and she said oh yeah I
talked to them at rebel wisdom and they
say oh wow they're so that they're
always saying how they're so left-wing
and they're all saying how the world's
like really going to hell and it's like
guys he looked outside recently
I mean existential risk and systematic
casket like that's not it surely that's
not a fringe position now like for a
long time it was and I was actually I
never went down that rabbit hole as much
as say I think Peters went down a lot
more and I know our mutual friend Daniel
Thorson did a lot on his podcast and
felt that he was kind of following this
thread of kind of existential risk and I
was quite resistant to that I didn't go
down that far but but now I'm like yeah
that's I'm seeing it all play out like
Daniel smacked and Berger talks about
exponential tech on a finite playing
field is self terminating and that's
what I'm saying mostly in the kind of my
focus is mostly on the information
ecology because I think that's that's
the the source of a lot of what we're
seeing but it feels to me like
weaponized information weaponized
disinformation like the planned emic
film being a perfect example of like
something that's incredibly sticky it's
incredibly compelling but it's playing
the game a self-destructive game it's
it's like its limbic hijack it's highly
emotive language whether or not it's
true try and untie us as I said before
I'm trying to take out the whether or
not these narratives are true and just
look at what's happening to us from a
from a kind of meta perspective so I was
a bit of a run
but well thanks a lot oh I'd love to ask
more I'm gonna let you go so we have it
we should close out soon we have five
minutes but I'll just maybe hand it back
to you David is there anything you want
you like I'm curious where rebel wisdom
is going content wise try mine this this
next video you want tease us a little
bitter here no um well it's about
conspiracies again I'm trying to look at
the the it's a piece about spirituality
and conspiracy right
is this a new phenomenon that we're
seeing kind of post David Icke or sorry
post I think we're seeing a new
phenomenon I think we're seeing like we
all knew what the Infowars Alex Jones
thing was I think we're seeing something
new and it's sort of it's love
consciousness awakening and at the same
time this evil cult is out to kill us
all and I think that's a new phenomenon
so I'm trying to do a film about that
and people are not gonna like it but
it's but it's what I'm honestly seeing
and what I'm trying to and I'm also
bringing in the concept of spiritual
spiritual like genuine spiritual
awakening in that because I think people
have a taste of questioning the
mainstream narrative and then we can
easily fall into over what's the word
like making sense too quickly on the
other side of that and that's what I'm
trying to convey with that film it's
like using the concept of spiritual
emergency the concept of genuine
awakening how can we hold an open frame
and I don't want to kind of dismiss all
of the conspiracy narratives because I'm
yeah I believe some of them are are true
there's but it's it's a secular religion
and people are as touchy about it as
people would be if you go into a
Christian convention and start
criticizing Christianity so
and that in like that to it that in
itself is a fascinating phenomenon can
we talk about how it's how it attracts
levels of certainty that are religious
in nature without triggering people no
you can't do it without triggering
people you will trigger people so maybe
maybe I close down the comments I don't
know what that's gonna drum so people
even more yeah I would love to see like
you know hardcore people who are into
the pair up little space or conspiracy
theory space and people from the blue
church that criticize it I would love to
have to see a conversation somehow
between
creating those two people are
representatives of it and so the rebel
wisdom festivals coming next weekend as
well yes yes so you can speak about it
or I'm doing something there I think
dialogue was we're trying to bake here
whatever so you can check out that link
I think people can still sign up yes you
can sign up so Ally so we've done two
really really good events we did two
one-day events as a kind of trial for it
and Ally has been working really hard on
the rebel wisdom festival and wants it
to be the best online event has ever
existed so and some people said that the
first one day ones that we did was some
of the best one-day events they've been
to so that's a cool awesome yeah looking
forward to for it and seeing everyone
there David thanks so much my friend for
coming on to the store today I was a
lovely chunky yeah so for everyone else
upcoming events we had the side view
launch party tomorrow with Adam Robert
at 6:30 p.m. Eastern Time the third
version of the side view is coming up I
had a medic mediation piece there we're
gonna have like a party I need to Roy's
coming all these interested people are
coming Joshua fields our buddy David
Joshua fields is coming in on Thursday
2:30 p.m. Eastern time on trauma truth
and technology and then we have a
relational exegesis event we're gonna
read a text together Keith Jones tells
impro our improv wherever it's called at
4 p.m. Eastern Time that's on Thursday
as well alright everyone thanks so much
for coming out today
greatly appreciate it ok